John Ray Martinez

AWS Certified Machine Learning Specialist with experience in recommendation systems, NLP, and time series. Recipient of Outstanding Graduate Student Award, College of Computing & Informatics Drexel University in 2021. Data Professional with more than a decade of software engineering experience and a teaching background in Physics.



martinez.jray@gmail.com

+12675961925

Salt Lake City, United States of America

...

www.jraymartinez.com

•

linkedin.com/in/johnraymartinez

WORK EXPERIENCE

Machine Learning AI Engineer Nicholas & Company

07/2021 - Present

(2 years) Salt Lake City UT, USA

Achievements/Tasks

- Build the machine learning infrastructure and recommendation systems from the ground up.
- Develop and implement machine learning products to support the eCommerce recommendation system and personalization experience for nicco-online customers.
- Maintain AWS Redshift, HVR, Matillion, and Looker applications and develops, tests, implements needed Boomi integration solutions.

Data Scientist

DXC Technology (Applied AI Center of Excellence)

09/2019 - 06/2021

(2 years) Philadelphia PA, USA

Achievements/Tasks

- Develop and deploy predictive models that provide predictions about resolution time interval of service tickets.
- Develop a multiple linear regression with Kalman filtering model for projecting COVID19 risk down to an individual employee level.

Senior IT Consultant

Safeway Philtech Inc (through IT Manager's Inc)

01/2016 - 09/2019

(3.5 years) Mandaluyong, Philippines

Achievements/Tasks

 Work for Merger Accounting team using Unix and DB2. The project involves analysis, development, maintenance, and stabilization of various accounting applications as a result of the Albertsons and Safeway merger.

Senior Software Engineer

Software International Corporation (M) Sdn Bhd

08/2014 - 12/2015

(1.5 year) Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia

Achievements/Tasks

 Serve as the lead application developer for the SAP conversion project, spearheading the analysis, development, and modification of the Insurance's Loans and Claims System.

Senior Software Engineer

J.P. Morgan Chase & Co. (through Seven Seven Softwares Inc)

05/2010 - 07/2014

(4 years) Pasig, Philippines

Achievements/Tasks

 Spearhead the enhancement and conversion projects, overseeing UAT and Production batch processing initiatives such as automation.

SKILLS



EDUCATION

Master of Science in Data Science Drexel University

09/2019 - 06/2021

Philadelphia, PA, USA

Cumulative GPA: 4.0

- Recipient of <u>2021 Outstanding Graduate Student Award, Drexel CCI</u>.
- Publish an international paper "The Impact of driver distraction and secondary tasks with and without other co-occurring driving behaviors on the level of road traffic crashes" in the best journal of 'Human Factors and Ergonomics' according to Scimago Journal Ranking (Accident Analysis and Prevention).
- Capstone Project: "Multimodal Brain Tumor Segmentation using Convolutional Neural Network" which was selected for oral research presentation at the 2021 <u>Drexel Emerging Graduate Scholars</u> Conference.

Bachelor of Science in Physics with Specialization in Computer Applications

De La Salle University - Manila

05/2002 - 08/2006

Taft Manila, Philippines

Bachelor of Secondary Education Major in Mathematics

De La Salle University - Manila

05/2002 - 08/2006

Taft Manila, Philippines

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Physics Instructor (06/2008 - 05/2009)

Physics Department, Central Mindanao University, Maramag, Bukidnon Philippines Teach university physics to students in engineering and the sciences.

Physics Instructor (06/2007 - 05/2008)

National Institute of Physics, University of the Philippines, Quezon City Philippines Teach university physics to students in engineering and the sciences.